Welcome back to a push in under three
minutes. No time for intros. Let's get
into it. Unit 6 is here and we
transition into a new time period of
American history. We covered
antibbellum, the civil war, and
reconstruction, which are all viable
eras of American history. Now, we
transition into a new era called the
Gilded Age. This era will be explored
throughout this unit. But the biggest
thing to notice is that the US will
slowly start becoming controlled by the
rich throughout this era, not the
government. Of course, there will be
three big causes of this. Westward
expansion, the industrial revolution and
capitalism. Right now, we will simply
talk about the westward expansion part
of it. So, let's recap. The Civil War
and reconstruction has ended. Yes, this
has left devastation all around the
country, but it also has left one other
big thing, an unbelievable level of
manufacturing. The big things here were
factories, steel, and railroads.
Railroads were especially exciting
because they could move a lot of goods
very fast, and the government made them
cheap to build. And that is why the
transcontinental railroad was ordered to
be built from the east to the west. Why
go to the west, you ask? It's simple.
Gold. So much gold was found in places
like modern-day Colorado, California,
Nevada, and many other places that many
settlers saw as a chance to get rich. It
also helped that at this time it was
really easy to move west because the
government still had the Homestead Act
in place along with various subsidies to
incentivize expansion. Farmers got a
bunch of new farming innovations like
barbed wire and steamed powered
equipment. And most importantly, the
West offered new land to farm and mine
on. With thousands of people moving
west, many communities formed. I
personally cannot be asked to go over
them, but here are some if you really
care to read about them. Now, here's
where things get muddy. Though there
isn't a technical start of the Guilded
Age, this is how the Guilded Age
essentially starts. There's only one way
a farmer or minor in the West is going
to transport their goods back to the
East. Railroads. The owners of these
railroads knew this and raised the
prices on everyone, especially small
businesses. This led to farmers creating
groups and alliances such as the
Graange, the Farmers Alliance, and the
Coward Farmers Alliance. But remember
what I said earlier, the rich are in
control in this time period. And so it's
no surprise that all of these for the
most part failed. In this time period,
farmers relied on bank loans and the
influx of farming goods caused prices to
drop, making it so farmers suffered
quite a bit from debt. Remember, this
video is only one of three separate
causes of the Guilded Age. There are
still others you have to consider, but
as for now, on the screen now are some
AP style questions for this topic. Pause
now.
I'll put the answers on the screen now.
I will see you in the next one.